A Finding Aid to the Bertha Schaefer Papers and Gallery Records, 1909-1975, bulk 1940-1965, in the Archives of American Art AAA.schabert
Archives of American Art
Bertha Schaefer papers and gallery records
bulk 1940-1965
1909-1975
AAA.schabert
Archives of American Art
4.6 Linear feet
The Bertha Schaefer papers and gallery records measure 4.6 linear feet and date from 1909-1975, with the bulk of the material dating from 1940-1965. The collection documents the Bertha Schaefer Gallery as well as Bertha Schaefer, the interior designer, through correspondence with artists and galleries, artist files, client files, exhibition material, printed material, financial material, biographical material, photographs, and six scrapbooks.
Schaefer, Bertha, 1895-1971
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Bertha Schaefer papers and gallery records were donated in several installments from 1969 to 1974 by Bertha Schaefer and Bertha Schaefer Gallery Inc. Paul Creamer donated three scrapbooks from the Bertha Schaefer Gallery and the New Bertha Schaefer Gallery in 1979. Additional material was donated in 1984 by Syracuse University.
Separated Materials note
Originals of loaned material concerning Alfred H. Maurer, including a scrapbook about Maurer from 1946 to 1969, were returned to Bertha Schaefer after microfilming. Loaned material is available on reel N69-115, but is not described in the container listing of this finding aid.
Originals of loaned material concerning Hale Woodruff, including correspondence, sketches and drawings, articles, photographs, catalogs, announcements, clippings, notes kept while student of Diego Rivera, and scrapbook, were returned to Hale Woodruff after microfilming (and the scrapbook to the Bertha Schaefer Gallery). Loaned material is available on reel N70-60, but is not described in the container listing of this finding aid.
Related Archival Materials note
Also found in the Archives of American Art is an oral history interview with Bertha Schaefer conducted by Paul Cummings, April 20-22, 1970.
Scope and Contents note
The Bertha Schaefer papers and gallery records measure 4.6 linear feet and date from 1909-1975, with the bulk of the material dating from 1940-1965. The collection documents the Bertha Schaefer Gallery as well as Bertha Schaefer, the interior designer, through correspondence with artists and galleries, artist files, client files, exhibition material, printed material, financial material, biographical material, photographs, and six scrapbooks. Also found here are oversized blue prints and sketched plans of interior design projects, as well as a number of oversized photographic prints and stereo slides. Correspondence contains handwritten notes by many notable artists, including Marcel Duchamp, Pablo Picasso, Jackson Pollock, Ad Reinhardt, and Fernando Zobel, with a bulk of the letters from Balcomb Greene.
Separated into three series, the Bertha Schaefer Gallery records document the artists represented by and function of the Bertha Schaefer Gallery. The Bertha Schaefer papers pertain to Bertha Schaefer as an interior designer through a large number of photographic materials and client files. Six scrapbooks document artists Will Barnet, Ben-Zion, Balcomb Greene, and Nicolai Vasilieff, as well as the Bertha Schaefer gallery and the New Bertha Schaefer Gallery.
Biographical/Historical note
Bertha Schaefer (1895-1971) was an interior designer and director of the Bertha Schaefer Gallery in New York, New York. Schaefer was born in Yazoo City, Mississippi to Emil and Julia (Marx) Schaefer. She received her B.A. on June 1, 1914 from Mississippi State College for Women, and received a diploma for interior decorating from the Parsons School of Design in New York City. In 1924, after living in Paris for 5 months, she opened Bertha Schaefer Interiors in New York. In 1944, she opened the Bertha Schaefer Gallery of Contemporary Art, which featured American and European paintings and sculpture. “The Modern House Comes Alive” (1947-1948) is one of the key exhibitions she created. Schaefer designed furniture for Joe Singer of M. Singer and Sons Furniture Company in New York, 1950-1961.
Schaefer won design awards from the Museum of Modern Art (1952) and the Decorators Club of New York (1959). In 1958, she was given an award of recognition from the U.S. Department of State for her gallery’s assistance in the American program for the Brussels Universal and International Exhibition, and an outstanding achievement in interior design award from the American Institute of Interior Designers. She was a member of several design organizations, including: the American Institute of Decorators, the Home Lighting Forum, the Illuminating Engineers Society, the American Federation of the Arts, and the Art Dealers Association of America. She was the president of the Decorators Club of New York from 1947-1948 and 1955-1957.
Schaefer was one of the first people to use fluorescent lighting in domestic spaces, with Percy Block as her first client, in 1939. In honor of Edison’s birthday in 1953, she designed a bathroom for General Electric, applying new developments in lighting. She died on May 24, 1971, after which the gallery was renamed the New Bertha Schaefer Gallery.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Arrangement note
This collection is arranged as 3 series. Records are generally arranged by material type and chronologically thereafter.
Series 1: Bertha Schaefer Gallery Records, 1909-1971 (0.8 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 2: Bertha Schaefer Papers, 1914-1971 (2.6 linear feet; Boxes 1-3, 6-7, OV 8-9)
Series 3: Scrapbooks, 1944-1975 (1.2 linear feet; Boxes 3-5)
Existence and Location of Copies note
Portions of the collection are available on 35 mm microfilm reels, N69-126, 42, 271, and 2129, at the Archives of American Art offices, and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of the collection as described in this finding aid may not reflect the order of the collection on microfilm due to reprocessing.
Barnet, Will, 1911-2012; Ben-Zion; Bertha Schaefer Gallery (New York, N.Y.).; Duchamp, Marcel, 1887-1968; Greene, Balcomb, 1904-1990; New Bertha Schaefer Gallery (New York, N.Y.).; Picasso, Pablo, 1881-1973; Pollock, Jackson, 1912-1956; Reinhardt, Ad, 1913-1967; Vasilieff, Nicholas; Zóbel, Fernando; Art galleries, Commercial -- New York (State)-- New York; Art, Modern -- 20th century -- New York (State) -- New York; Gallery directors; Gallery owners; Interior decoration--New York (State)--New York; Interior decorators; Painters; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Sculptors; Sketches
- Bertha Schaefer Gallery Records, bulk 1950-1970; 1909-1971; Series 1; 0.8 Linear feet Box 1
  Arrangement note
  This series consists of 5 subseries, and is arranged alphabetically where possible, and chronologically thereafter.
  1.1 Correspondence, 1932-1971
  1.2 Artist Files, 1909-1970
  1.3 Exhibition Files, 1945-1966
  1.4 Printed Material, 1923-1968
  1.5 Photographs, circa 1950-1958
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence includes handwritten and typed letters to and from Bertha Schaefer and Bertha Schaefer Gallery, from artists, publishers, universities, galleries, etc. There are letters, cards, and postcards, mostly addressed to Bertha Schaefer and concerning the gallery. Some correspondence may concern personal matters, but also concern gallery sales, artist representation by the Bertha Shaefer Gallery, artworks shipped, received, and exhibited. A bulk of the correspondence is from Balcomb Greene, and one folder is dedicated to correspondence from Dorothy Farr. Additionally, there are letters from many notable artists. Of note: an undated, handwritten letter from Marcel Duchamp; a letter dated August 26, 1963 written from Madrid and signed "Pablo" (presumed to be Pablo Picasso) and addresses his art dealer, Aime Maeght, and Bertha Schaefer's previously stated unwillingness "to deal with him"; a letter dated June 6, 1966 from Ad Reinhardt; and a letter dated October 14, 1948 from Jackson Pollock.
  Also included are artist files on a small number of the artists who exhibited their work at the gallery; exhibition materials, including catalogs, announcements, posters, and some specific exhibitions; printed material and clippings; and four photographs -- of Bertha Schaefer in a souvenir photo at Mackinac Island, Schaefer in a group photo at the Brooklyn Museum's "14 Painter-Printmakers" exhibition, a color photo of a house in South Carolina, and one photo of Hale Woodruff's "Figure" painting. Note that the printed material may contain clippings referencing Bertha Schaefer as an interior designer. See Box 3 for more printed material and clippings pertaining to interior design.
  - Correspondence, bulk 1950-1970; 1932-1971; 1.1
    Included here are handwritten and typewritten letters both to and from Bertha Schaefer concerning the Bertha Schaefer Gallery, artists represented, artists inquiring about shows, artwork sold, etc. The bulk of the correspondence is from abstract painter Balcomb Greene.
    - Correspondence, 1932-1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 2)
      (Includes a letter from Marcel Duchamp)
    - Correspondence, 1940-1957 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, circa 1946-circa 1966 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      (Bulk of letters from Balcomb Greene)
    - Correspondence, 1948-1959 (Box 1, Folder 5-9)
      (Includes a letter from Jackson Pollock)
    - Correspondence, circa 1958-1967 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      (Includes a letter from Fernando Zobel)
    - Correspondence, 1960-1967 (Box 1, Folder 11-19)
      (Includes a letter from Pablo Picasso and a letter from Ad Reinhardt)
    - Correspondence, 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 20-23)
    - Correspondence, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 24-26)
    - Correspondence - From Dorothy Farr, 1953-1961 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Artist Files, bulk 1950-1965; 1909-1970; 1.2
    Included here are price lists and inventories, artist bios, photographs of artists and artwork, exhibition announcements and catalogs, clippings, and printed material.
    - Ben-Zion, 1942-1964 (Box 1, Folder 28-29)
    - Alfred Jensen, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Roger Jorgensen, circa 1965-1970 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Alfred Maurer, 1909-1935 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Aline Rhonie, circa 1960 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Henry Toledano, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Exhibition Files, 1945-1966; 1.3
    Found here are files concerning two exhibitions: "The Modern House Comes to Life" and "Self-Portrait Sculptures by the Blind Exhibition," which include photographs of artwork, press releases, exhibition announcements, correspondence, and clippings.
    - "The Modern House Comes to Life" (1947-1949) (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - "Self-Portrait Sculptures by the Blind" (1950), 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 36-37)
  - Printed Material, bulk 1954-1965; 1923-1968; 1.4
    Included here are clippings, press releases, exhibition announcements and catalogs, and a magazine article typescript.
    - News Clippings, 1923-1968 (Box 1, Folder 38-44)
    - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1945-1966 (Box 1, Folder 45-47)
    - Press Releases and Magazine Article Typescript, 1954-1964 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Photographs, circa 1950-1958; 1.5
    Found here are four photographs -- of Bertha Schaefer in a souvenir photo at Mackinac Island, Schaefer in a group photo at the Brooklyn Museum's "14 Painter-Printmakers" exhibition, a color photo of a house in South Carolina, and one photo of Hale Woodruff's "Figure" painting.
    - Photographs, circa 1950-1958 (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Bertha Schaefer Papers, bulk 1947-1960; 1914-1971; Series 2; 2.6 Linear feet Boxes 1-3, 6-7, OV 8-9
  This series consists of 6 subseries and is arranged alphabetically when possible, and chronologically thereafter.
  2.1: Client Files, circa 1947-1965
  2.2: Financial Material, 1930-1968
  2.3: Photographs, circa 1947-1959
  2.4: Biographical Material, 1914-1971
  2.5: Writings, 1947-1965
  2.6: Printed Material, 1922-1971
  Included here are materials pertaining to Bertha Schaefer as an interior designer, furniture designer, and designer of innovative lighting.
  Client files contain individuals and companies for whom Schaefer worked as an interior designer, and includes sketches, blueprints, fabric, tile, carpet, wallpaper, and color samples; financial material contains invoices and supplies purchased for interior designing projects. An extensive number of photographs of interior design spaces include oversized prints, stereo slides, and color transparencies. Biographical material contains certificates of graduation, awards, recognitions, invitations, resumes, and death condolences. Writings contain annotated typescripts and drafts of lectures and speeches given by Bertha Schaefer and David Porter; printed material concerns interior design shows, furniture designs, lighting designs, biographical sketches, all in newspaper or magazine clippings. Note that some of the printed material may also contain Bertha Schaefer Gallery references.
  - Client Files, circa 1947-1965; 2.1
    Included here are files pertaining to individuals and companies for whom Bertha Schaefer conducted interior design projects. Materials include fabric, tile, wallpaper, wooden shade, and carpet samples, as well as sketches, plans, and blue prints. Folders are arranged alphabetically.
    - Mrs. Appleget, circa 1950s (Box 1, Folder 50-51)
    - Mrs. Jacob A. Begner, circa 1955 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Bing and Bing, circa 1958 (Box 1, Folder 53-54)
      (Oversized material housed in OV 8-9)
    - Frances T. Cahn, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Mrs. Howard Cullman, circa 1950s (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Mrs. Louis S. Davidson, circa 1950s (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Mr. and Mrs. Charles Diamond, circa 1950s (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Mrs. Saul F. Dribben, circa 1950s (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Mrs. Angelika W. Frink, circa 1962 (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
    - General Electric Bathroom (BBDO), 1953 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      (Oversized material housed in OV 9)
    - Col. and Mrs. William W. Goodman, circa 1950 (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
    - Mrs. Monroe Gutman, circa 1950s (Box 2, Folder 7-9)
    - Haffenreffer, circa 1950 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Mrs. Herbert Haldenstein, circa 1955 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      (Oversized material housed in OV 8)
    - Mr. and Mrs. C. W. Harrison, 1957-1964 (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
    - Sidney Hechinger, 1937-1940 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Sidney Hechinger, circa 1947 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Mrs. Eric D. Hirsch, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Mrs. Harris Jones, circa 1950s (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Mrs. J. M. Kaplan, circa 1957 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Mr. and Mrs. Alex Kerman, circa 1950s (Box 2, Folder 19-20)
    - Mr. Milton W. King - Office, circa 1950 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Mr. Milton W. King - Photographs, circa 1950 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Mr. and Mrs. Thomas B. Leman, 1954-1963 (Box 2, Folder 23-24)
    - Mr. and Mrs. Thomas B. Leman - Plans and Sketches, 1954-1963 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Mrs. John Nettleton, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - The New York Times - Rooms, circa 1950s (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Paris Apartment, 1961-1965 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Mrs. Samuel J. Rosensohn, circa 1938 (Box 2, Folder 29-30)
    - Marx Schaefer, circa 1950s (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Mrs. Carl Stern, circa 1959 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Mrs. E. P. Townsend, circa 1950s (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Mrs. Alan Warshow, 1957-1959 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Mr. and Mrs. Milton Weinberg, circa 1950s (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Oversized: Bing and Bing, Removed from Box 1, Folder 54 (Box OV 8-9)
    - Oversized: General Electric Bathroom (BBDO), Removed from Box 2, Folder 4 (Box OV 9)
    - Oversized: Mrs. Herbert Haldenstein, Removed from Box 2, Folder 11 (Box OV 8)
    - Oversized: Mr. and Mrs. C. W. Harrison, Removed from Box 2, Folder 12 (Box OV 8-9)
    - Oversized: Mrs. Eric D. Hirsch, Removed from Box 2, Folder 16 (Box OV 8)
    - Oversized: Mr. and Mrs. Thomas B. Lemann, Removed from Box 2, Folder 25 (Box OV 8-9)
    - Oversized: Mrs. Carl Stern, Removed from Box 2, Folder 32 (Box OV 9)
  - Financial Material, 1930-1968; 2.2
    Found here are materials relating to some of Bertha Schaefer's interior design projects, including invoices, receipts, and supplies lists.
    - Interior Design Financial Material, 1930-1968 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, circa 1947-1959; 2.3
    Found here are color transparencies, snapshots, stereo slides, and large and oversized black and white photographic prints of Bertha Schaefer's interior design projects. Folders are primarily arranged chronologically.
    - Interior Design Photographs, circa 1947-1948 (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
    - Stereo Slides - Gutman Apartment, circa 1950s (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Stereo Slides - Schwarz Apartment, circa 1950s (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Stereo Slides - Perrin Apartment, circa 1950s (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Color Transparencies of Interiors Photographs, circa 1950s (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Stereo Slides - National Home Furnishings Show, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 8-9)
    - Stereo Slides - Saks Fifth Avenue Window, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Stereo Slides - Home Furnishing Shows, 1952-1953 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Interior Design Photographs, 1952-1959 (Box 3, Folder 12-13)
    - Stereo Slides - Home Furnishings Show, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Stereo Slides - "Paris in New York", 1954 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Interior Design Photographs, 1954-1958 (Box 3, Folder 16-17)
    - Oversized Photograph of Jackson Pollock and Lee Krasner, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Oversized Photographs of Interior Designs, 1931-1960 (Box 6, Folder 2-8)
    - Oversized Photographs of Interior Designs, 1937-1950 (Box 7, Folder 1-7)
  - Biographical Material, 1914-1971; 2.4
    Included here are materials concerning Bertha Schaefer, the individual, such as certificates of awards, diplomas, invitations, resumes, miscellaneous notes, and condolences upon her death in 1971.
    - Biographical Material, 1914-1971 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Oversized: Biographical Material, Removed from Box 3, Folder 18 (Box OV 8)
  - Writings, 1947-1965; 2.5
    Found here are typescripts of speeches and talks given by Schaefer and by David Porter, including annotations and drafts, and some magazine article typescripts.
    - Writings by Bertha Schaefer, 1947-1963 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Writings by David Porter, 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Printed Material, 1922-1971; 2.6
    Found here are magazine and newspaper article clippings pertaining to Bertha Schaefer's interior design, furniture design, and lighting design projects. Folders are arranged chronologically.
    - Clippings - Miscellaneous and Articles, 1922-1964 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Clippings - Magazine Articles, circa 1948-1957 (Box 3, Folder 22-24)
    - Clippings - Magazine Articles and Catalog, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Clippings, 1965-1971 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Scrapbooks, 1944-1975; Series 3; 1.2 Linear feet Boxes 3-5
  Found here are scrapbooks for Will Barnet, Ben-Zion, Balcomb Greene, and Nicolai Vaselieff, as well as for the Bertha Schaefer Gallery and the New Bertha Schaefer Gallery. Scrapbooks include a variety of materials such as newspaper and magazine clippings, exhibition materials, and some exhibition and artist catalogs.
  Scrapbooks are arranged alphabetically by artist, followed by the Bertha Schaefer Gallery and the New Bertha Schaefer Gallery.
  - Scrapbook, Will Barnet, 1946-1963 (Box 3, Folder 27-33)
  - Scrapbook, Ben-Zion, 1946-1959 (Box 3, Folder 34-36)
  - Scrapbook, Balcomb Greene, 1945-1961 (Box 3, Folder 37-41)
  - Scrapbook, Balcomb Greene, 1945-1961 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Scrapbook, Nicolai Vasilieff, 1947-1951 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook, Bertha Schaefer Gallery, 1944-1963 (Box 4, Folder 4-13)
  - Scrapbook, Bertha Schaefer Gallery, 1956-1971 (Box 5, Folder 1-9)
  - Scrapbook, New Bertha Schaefer Gallery, 1972-1975 (Box 5, Folder 10-11)